<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-30T11:29:11-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kunal Rai</title><subtitle>A website about me</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Current Projects :sweat_smile:</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/new-projects/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Current Projects :sweat_smile:" /><published>2020-07-29T22:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-29T22:10:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/new-projects</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/new-projects/">&lt;!-- &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; src=&quot;https://www.lockheedmartin.com/content/dam/lockheed-martin/aero/photo/F-35/F35Direct_PR.jpg&quot;&gt;

&lt;/p&gt; --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-in-progress&quot;&gt;Work in Progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out sometimes you start things that don’t go anywhere or sometimes you get beat to market :anguished:.
Anyway, it is still a fun journey. Some recent projects I worked on were unlucky, and I decided to take a break from those to explore new paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on a couple of projects for my own interest.
One of them is improving my music selection on Spotify because I got tired of Discover Weekly and Release Radar and could not get good recommendations from their song radio feature. :dancer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another is looking at the intersections of politically divisive hashtags :collision: or hashtags that are commonly associated with one view or another. I am just trying to get a feel for what kind of discussion is created if at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kunalrai</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html">&amp;lt;!– &amp;lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&amp;gt;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Research @ Jones Business School :sunglasses:</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research @ Jones Business School :sunglasses:" /><published>2020-06-15T22:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-15T22:10:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;128&quot; src=&quot;http://rankings.ft.com/lib/img/logos/entity/rice-university-jones&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an ongoing project that I am working on with a Professor of Finance at the Jones Graduate School of Business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-about-pandas&quot;&gt;Learning about Pandas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting my research position was my introduction to data analysis and manipulation with Python. I quickly learned about Pandas, Spark, Linux, and the many tools available from those libraries/softwares. Working with large amounts of data was new to me and learning how to use dataframes to work with the data easily was among the first steps I took. Further the value of visualization of the data through libraries like seaborn and matplotlib gave me a better idea of what I was working with and what the next steps should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;continual-work&quot;&gt;Continual Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I started research, I have skilled up significantly through research, my classes, and internships. From learning the basics of pandas I am now working with NLP techniques to look at corporate datasets for insights.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kunalrai</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Graphic Design :art:</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/graphic-design/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Graphic Design :art:" /><published>2020-01-23T22:10:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-23T22:10:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/graphic-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/graphic-design/">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; src=&quot;https://mir-s3-cdn-cf.behance.net/project_modules/max_1200/a008e375908053.5d546a110405b.png&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-portfolio&quot;&gt;My Portfolio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to check out some of the designs described below, feel free to check out my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.behance.net/ksrai9914a6&quot;&gt;Behance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-started&quot;&gt;How I started&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphic design is something that I have taken from ideation to fruition, multiple times starting in high school. Design has always interested me, beginning with my introduction to Google’s material design update when I had an android. Seeing firsthand how the design itself of the OS affected the user experience drew me in. From there, I started to pickup Photoshop and redesigned my robotics program logos and STEM program’s website in high school. Since then, I have cultivated my interest by further developing my design skills through more projects and learning more about the field continually.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kunalrai</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decline Curve Analysis @ Chevron :chart_with_downwards_trend:</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/decline-curve-analysis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decline Curve Analysis @ Chevron :chart_with_downwards_trend: " /><published>2019-08-02T22:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T22:10:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/decline-curve-analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/decline-curve-analysis/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-decline-curve-analysis&quot;&gt;What is Decline Curve Analysis?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decline curve analysis (DCA) is a technique commonly used by oil and gas companies to be able to forecast production of an oil well. DCA typically looks at a plot of rate versus time to find where the production will intersect the x-axis, which is the point at which the production output is no longer of value or significant. The integral of this curve provides the EUR or expected ultimate recovery / reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-can-you-do-decline-curve-analysis-on-non-declining-wells&quot;&gt;How can you do ‘decline curve analysis’ on non-declining wells?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a puzzle for me as well initially. However, as with most ML problems, manipulation of the data was the most important part of cracking the model. Using the data available, I did a lot of feature engineering to determine what data was useful and what data was not in determining future production of these wells. After finding the most valuable features, I ran through multiple regression models such as XGBoost, Random Forest, Ridge Regressor, as well as using Data Robot to streamline the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools-i-used-to-create-the-model&quot;&gt;Tools I used to create the model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used a combination of Python (pandas, pyspark, scikit-learn, seaborn), SQL, a linux cluster, Azure, and DataRobot to create the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;results-and-takeaways&quot;&gt;Results and Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By learning about machine learning &amp;amp; data science workflows I was able to figure out best practices and make progress towards creating a model. My model ultimately had a 25% mean absolute error on the future production of wells that were non-declining and will be integrated into the product that handles all forecasting of oil wells. Through the modeling process I was able to learn the importance of understanding the data through visualization, model creation, hyperparameter tuning, and feature engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kunalrai</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tool Development @ Lockheed Martin :hammer:</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/tool-development/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tool Development @ Lockheed Martin :hammer:" /><published>2018-05-08T22:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-08T22:10:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tool-development</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/tool-development/">&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; src=&quot;https://www.lockheedmartin.com/content/dam/lockheed-martin/aero/photo/F-35/F35Direct_PR.jpg&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-a-standalone-tool&quot;&gt;Creating a standalone tool&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first project at LM Aeronautics was to develop a standalone tool that created a monetary value for software updates that were made to the F-35. I had to take a dataset of past software changes that had a calculated monetary value and determine how to predict the value that a new software update would provide. Since this software was related to the performance of a physical fighter jet, there were quite a few variables to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to come up with predictions, I had to understand how the current predictions were being calculated. I took a period to understand the factors, meet with SME’s who provided data, and pre-process the data before developing the tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;development&quot;&gt;Development&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to software constraints, I had to open myself to new development options. Given that the tool needed to be portable and the output easily understandable for presentation, I decided to pickup Visual Basic for Applications and develop the tool in an excel spreadsheet. It was very different coming from Python but I was able to learn quite a bit about the limitations and benefits of my choice. Ultimately, the tool had a simple GUI, worked quickly and intuitively, while producing predictions of value within 15% of the actual value.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kunalrai</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>